<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
    <properties>
        <author>Lyudmila Balakireva</author>
        <title>SiteStory Transactional Web Archive</title>
    </properties>
 <head>
    <meta name="keyword" content="transactional web archive, java, sitestory"/>
</head>
    <body>
        <section name="Idea and Concept">
            <p>
             Transactional Archiving consists of selectively capturing and storing transactions that take place  between a web client (browser) and a web server.  </p>
             <p>Most existing web archives recurrently send out bots to crawl the content of web servers. This results in observations of a server's content at the time of crawling. Since the crawling frequency is generally not aligned with the change rate of a server's resources, this approach is typically not able to capture all versions of a server's resource. The resulting archive may provide an acceptable overview of a server's evolution over time, but it will not provide an accurate representation of the server's entire history. A SiteStory Archive, however, captures every version of a resource as it is being requested by a browser.  The resulting archive is effectively representative of a server's entire history, although versions of resources that are never requested by a browser will also never be archived. </p>


            <p>The SiteStory Archive  provides the following opportunities:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Dynamic Archiving of your Apache Web Content Server</li>
                <li>Archive accessible via the Memento protocol </li>
                <li>Archival data can be offloaded to WARC files</li>
                <li>Archival data can be uploaded into an instance of the Internet Archive's Wayback software</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="Architecture Overview">
            <p><img id="" class="figure" alt="Figure 1" src="images/site_story_pic2.png" title="Overview"/>
            </p>
        </section> 
    </body>
</document>